Guide to the Walter Ernst Meyerhof Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Walter Ernst Meyerhof papers
1948-1994
SC0551
Meyerhof, Walter E. (Walter Ernst), 1922-
25.5 Linear feet
The papers of Walter E. Meyerhof document his administrative, teaching, and research activities in the Department of Physics at Stanford; included are departmental records, correspondence, course materials, research files, grant files, committee minutes and records, reports, and reprints. Some of the class files are those of Prof. John D. Walecka.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Walter E. Meyerhof, 1998.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Walter E. Meyerhof earned his M.A. in physics in 1944 and Ph.D. in 1946 at the University of Pennsylvania. He taught at the University of Illinois, Urbana before joining the Stanford faculty in 1949. He retired from active teaching in 1992.
Description of the Collection
The papers of Walter E. Meyerhof document his administrative, teaching, and research activities in the Department of Physics at Stanford; included are departmental records, correspondence, course materials, research files, grant files, committee minutes and records, reports, and reprints. Some of the class files are those of Prof. John D. Walecka.
Access Terms
Meyerhof, Walter E. (Walter Ernst), 1922-; Stanford University. Department of Physics.; Walecka, John Dirk, 1932-; Nuclear physics.
Collection Contents
- Papers, Accession ARCH-1998-145
  ROUGH OVERVIEW OF BOXES
  1-5 Atomic Research
  5-8 Miscellaneous: minutes, project files, some unlabeled files
  8-13 Atomic Radiation
  14-16 Stanford courses
  16-20 Physics department files
  21-23 Department related, alpha files A - L
  24-26 Department related, alpha files M - R
  27-28 Department related, alpha files R - Z
  27-28 Miscellaneous files
  29-31 Faculty Reports
  29-31 Progress Reports
  29-31 Proposals
  31-35 Administrative files: purchase orders, abstracts, conferences, talks, manuscripts
  35-37 Administrative files
  35-37 Correspondence
  37-39 Administrative files
  37-39 Files from desk
  39-40 Files from desk
  37-39 41-44 Reprints; card file
  - Atomic Research: (Box 1)
    - MO Munich 1973 (Box 1)
    - Observ. of Z=70 Br+Br (Box 1)
    - Quasiatours (Box 1)
    - Auger – X Ray (Box 1)
    - Stopped Atom (Box 1)
    - MO Shape (Box 1)
    - AFO/MO x-ray proc. Belgrade 1973 (Box 1)
    - Conferences (Box 1)
    - Heidelberg (Box 1)
    - IX IC Peace IV ISIAC (Box 1)
    - Review Letters (Box 1)
    - Annual Reviews Article, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Position emission (Box 1)
    - Dilution experiments (Box 1)
    - MO Auisotropy (Box 1)
    - Pb-Pb MO Exp't (Box 1)
    - L-L level watching (Box 1)
    - K-L level watching (Box 1)
    - Multistep process (Box 1)
    - Thorson Plot (Box 1)
    - MO Carambole (Box 1)
    - 1976 Meetings (Box 1)
    - 80 Mev I+I (Box 1)
    - 1974, 1980 Meetings (Box 1)
    - US – Japan (Box 1)
    - 3dδ Ioniz. P(b) (Box 1)
    - 2 dδ Paper (II) (Box 1)
    - Science Article (Box 2)
    - Nuclear reaction Effects on Intershell Ionization (Draft) (Box 2)
    - 2 FEV 436 Progress report 1980/81 (Box 2)
    - 1 FEV 403 Germany / France (Box 2)
    - 1082/83 Progress report (Box 2)
    - U+U Berkeley, 1984/85 (Box 2)
    - Final report 1989 (Box 2)
    - Progress report 1984 (Box 2)
    - Facilities account # 3 2 FEV 443 (Box 2)
    - 1 FEV 402 (Box 2)
    - Computer proposal (Box 2)
    - Frankfurt / Bordeaux Coop. Program 1985/90, NSF 84-14671 (Box 2)
    - 2 FEV 435 - finished (Box 3)
    - NSF equipment proposal (Box 3)
    - ATO. Phys. Expenses Nov. 1980, 2 FEV 436 (Box 3)
    - 1994 proposal (Box 3)
    - Supplementary 1991 proposal, 2 FEV 448 (Box 3)
    - 2 FEV 449 SCAC FAB – University Memos etc. (Box 3)
    - Facilities account: 2 FEV 437/8; Computer proposal 2 FEV 440; 2 FEV 442 (Box 3)
    - Atomic physics expenses 2 FEV 442 (Box 4)
    - Frankfurt Coop. Prog. 1981-85 (Box 4)
    - 1987 proposal to NSF PHY-86-14650 (Box 4)
    - NSF 1984 Proposal (Box 4)
    - 2 FEV 444 (Box 4)
    - 2 FEV 445 Facilities account #4 (Box 4)
    - Proposed research plans for Van De Graff Lab (Box 4)
    - Meyerhof original proposal 2 FEV 436 (Box 4)
    - Progress report 1989/90 figures (Box 5)
    - CN proposal (Box 5)
    - 1984 Proposal (Box 5)
    - NSF Suppl. Proposal to 2, FEV 436 (Aug. 1983) (Box 5)
    - Atomic proposal (Box 5)
  - Women in Physics – Stanford U. (Box 5)
  - Minutes 1988/89 (Box 5)
  - Minutes 1986/7/8 (Box 5)
  - Astro search (Box 5)
  - Gravitation Com (Box 5)
  - Quantum Electronic search (Box 5)
  - SHOP (Box 5)
  - Davisson-Germer (Box 5)
  - Senate represent (Box 5)
  - Affirm. Action (Box 6)
  - Van De Graff Stanford (Box 6)
  - High Volt. Engineering Corp (Box 6)
  - Levine (Box 6)
  - Kirkpatrick resolution (Box 6)
  - Hofstadter Resolution (Box 6)
  - Meetings and invitations (Box 6)
  - Lecture Hall (Box 6)
  - Van de Graaf Building (empty) (Box 6)
  - Van de Graaf Use (Box 6)
  - Tandem optics (Box 6)
  - Grad. School Committee (Box 6)
  - Foil Changer Equip. Rebate (Box 7)
  - Everitt (Box 7)
  - Cranston, Frederic P. (Box 7)
  - Crasemann (Box 7)
  - Chain Hoists & Cranes (Box 7)
  - Bruch (Box 7)
  - Book (Box 7)
  - Blumenfeld (Box 7)
  - Advances in Ado/Mobe Phys. Articles (Box 7)
  - Amer. Phys. Soc., Am. Inst. Of Physics, etc. (Box 7)
  - Atomic Data (Box 7)
  - B-ray spectometer (Box 7)
  - Answer Book (Box 7)
  - 1994 references (Box 8)
  - Thoughts on classroom teaching (Box 8)
  - Physics 10 1972/3 (Box 8)
  - HEPL search (Box 8)
  - ICPEAC 1985 (Box 8)
  - References (Box 8)
  - References 1991/2 (Box 8)
  - Misc. papers (Box 8)
  - Compound... X-rays (Box 8)
  - Duinker effect (Box 9)
  - Memorandum & misc. (Box 9)
  - Metal-Metal contacts (Box 9)
  - Beta-Bay spectrometer (Box 9)
  - Be 9 (Box 9)
  - X-ray intensities (Box 9)
  - β ranger (Box 9)
  - Standard absorption curves (Box 9)
  - γ-γ angular correlation curves (Box 9)
  - Absorption coefficients (Box 9)
  - Standard curves – extra copies (Box 9)
  - No. I Detector Efficiencies (Box 9)
  - Energy spread in neutron producing reactions (Box 9)
  - "An Atom Smasher for Well Logging" by Philip W. Martin (Box 10)
  - Lamb – Advanced QM (Box 10)
  - G (UA) highly promoted MO's (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
  - Inelastic N scattering Zu, Ce (Box 10)
  - Cl 33 (Box 10)
  - As 71 (Box 10)
  - Ir 192 (Box 10)
  - e polarization (Box 10)
  - Radiation (Box 10)
  - Brower (Box 10)
  - Burch (Box 10)
  - Donahue (Box 10)
  - Felmann (Box 11)
  - Gove, Durser (Box 11)
  - Hoffmann (Box 11)
  - University Panel on Radiological Hazards (Box 11)
  - Hopkins (Box 11)
  - Mehlhorn (Box 11)
  - McDonald (Box 11)
  - Miller (Box 11)
  - Moore (Box 11)
  - Saris (Box 12)
  - Tucker (Box 12)
  - Physics 11 1979/80 (Box 12)
  - Lectures in ionization etc. (Box 12)
  - Physics 21 1987-90 (Box 12)
  - Physics 25 1989/90 (Box 13)
  - Physics 51 1967-68 (Box 13)
  - Physics 52-53. Electricity (Box 13)
  - Physics 55 set ups (Box 13)
  - Physics 57 1960/61 (Box 13)
  - Physics 55 Fall 91 (Box 14)
  - Physics 57 lectures (Box 14)
  - Physics 57 summer 1962 Exams/Problems (Box 14)
  - Physics 105 Solids (Box 14)
  - Physics 108 58/59 (Box 14)
  - Physics 140 1967-68 (Box 14)
  - Physics Nuclear Moment - Bloch (Box 14)
  - Themodynamics Physics 173 (Box 14)
  - Physics 175 (Box 15)
  - Stanford Physics 181 1950/51 (Box 15)
  - Physics 181 1951/52 (Box 15)
  - Physics 183 1953/54 (Box 15)
  - 185/7 1961-62 (Box 15)
  - Physics 240/1 1962/3 (Box 15)
  - Physics 240, Nuclear physics, Autumn 1965/66 (Box 15)
  - Physics 181 1972/73 (Box 15)
  - Physics 299 (Box 15)
  - Physics 260 1987 (Box 15)
  - Physics 260 Talk (Box 15)
  - Nuclear Physics 240-241, Stanford Univ., 1969/70 (Box 16)
  - Physics 241 Walecka (Box 16)
  - Physics 242 Walecka (Box 16)
  - Physics 243 Walecka (Box 16)
  - Curriculum Project (Box 16)
  - Minutes 1989-. (Box 16)
  - Grad. Study Committee (Box 16)
  - Minutes 1985-6 (Box 16)
  - Minutes 1984-5 (Box 17)
  - Minutes 1983 (Box 17)
  - Stipends 1979-83 (Box 17)
  - Minutes 1982 (Box 17)
  - Minutes 1981-82 (Box 17)
  - TA Survey 1979-80 (Box 17)
  - Minutes 1979/81 (Box 17)
  - Minutes 1977/79 (Box 17)
  - Grad. Students 1977-8 (Box 17)
  - Grad. Students 1975-6 (Box 17)
  - Professorial Committee 1976-77 (Box 17)
  - Grad Students 1976-77 (Box 17)
  - Grad Students 1974 (Box 18)
  - Grad Studies 1965-70 (Box 18)
  - Grad Studies 1972-74 (Box 18)
  - Grad Studies 1970-72 (Box 18)
  - Trial Tutorial System (Box 18)
  - Course Review (Physics) (Box 18)
  - Education Committee (Box 18)
  - Faculty Meetings 1975-77 (Box 18)
  - Faculty Meetings 1970-71 (Box 18)
  - Minutes of Meetings 1970-75 (Box 18)
  - Stanford 1969-70 (Box 18)
  - Stanford 1968-69 (Box 18)
  - Stanford 1961-72, misc. (Box 18)
  - Stanford 1967-68 (Box 19)
  - Education Committee (Box 19)
  - Stanford Minutes 1966-67 (Box 19)
  - Students 1965-66 (Box 19)
  - Stanford minutes 1965-66 (Box 19)
  - Students 1964-65 (Box 19)
  - Stanford minutes 1964-65 (Box 19)
  - Stanford minutes 1963-64 (Box 19)
  - Students 1963-64 (Box 19)
  - Stanford minutes 1962-63 (Box 19)
  - Students 1962-63 (Box 19)
  - Stanford minutes 1961-62 (Box 19)
  - Graduate students 1961-62 (Box 19)
  - Stanford minutes 1960-61 (Box 20)
  - Graduate students 1960-61 (Box 20)
  - Physics 51 discussions (Box 20)
  - Stanford minutes 1959-60 (Box 20)
  - Graduate students 1959-60 (Box 20)
  - Stanford minutes 1958-59 (Box 20)
  - Graduate students 1958-59 (Box 20)
  - Stanford minutes 1957-58 (Box 20)
  - Professional and Faculty meetings 1956-1957 (Box 20)
  - Graduate Study Committee (G.S.C.) 1956-57 (4 folders) (Box 20)
  - Physics Department 1956-57 (Box 20)
  - Undergraduate Study Comm. 1956-57 (Box 20)
  - Professional and Faculty Meetings 1953-56 (Box 20)
  - G.S.C. 1955-56 (4 folders), 1954-55 (3 folders), 1953-54 (3 folders) (Box 20)
  - Undergraduate Study Comm. 1953-56 (Box 20)
  - Physics Department 1953-56 (Box 20)
  - Professional and Faculty Meetings 1950-53 (Box 21)
  - G.S.C. 1952-53 (3 folders), 1951-52 (3 folders), 1950-51 (4 folders), and 1949-1950 (1 folder) (Box 21)
  - Physics Department 1950-53 (Box 21)
  - Undergraduate Study Comm. 1950-52 (Box 21)
  - Other, 1949-50 and prior to (Box 21)
  - High School Students (Box 21)
  - Dept. Grad. Study Comm: Minutes of Last Years, bound annually (Box 21)
  - Dept. Grad. Study Comm: loose minutes and other notes (Box 21)
  - APS Committee on Minorities (Box 21)
  - Anholt (Box 21)
  - Annual Review (Box 21)
  - Argonne (Box 21)
  - Andriamonte (Box 21)
  - Army Research (Box 22)
  - A.P.S. Nominating Committee (Box 22)
  - Auston, Sam (Box 22)
  - Baker (Box 22)
  - Berkeley (Box 22)
  - Becker, U. (Box 22)
  - Blatt (Box 22)
  - Bloch, Felix (Box 22)
  - Bloch committee (Box 22)
  - Bockelheide, Irving (Box 22)
  - Brun, Dr. Ernst (Box 22)
  - California Research Corp. (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - CAMS (Box 23)
  - CERN (Box 23)
  - Chase, Lloyd F., Jr. (Box 23)
  - Community college (Box 23)
  - Consulting (Box 23)
  - Consultants and visitors (Box 23)
  - Cyclotron (Box 23)
  - Danforth (Box 23)
  - Dale, Daniel Stanton (Box 23)
  - Employment (Box 23)
  - Frank Dietrich (Box 23)
  - Fairbank, William Martin (Box 23)
  - Gauntt (Box 23)
  - GUARDALA, N.A. (Box 23)
  - HLS Budget Advisory Group (Box 23)
  - S.S. Hanna (Box 23)
  - Tulane (Box 23)
  - Humboldt Foundation (Box 24)
  - Horen, Dan (Box 24)
  - Hülskötter (Box 24)
  - Kohler, Donald (Box 24)
  - Lockheed (Box 24)
  - McDonald, Robert (Box 24)
  - Meyerhoff - Dept. and personal (3 folders) (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 24)
  - Molitoris, J.D. (Box 24)
  - National Science Foundation (2 folders) (Box 25)
  - NSF research proposals (Box 25)
  - R. O'Neil (Box 25)
  - NSF Reports (Box 25)
  - NSF CP 2969 (Box 25)
  - NSF CP 5697 (Box 25)
  - OOR-ARO Reports, 1959 - (Box 26)
  - ONR status report (Box 26)
  - Pantell (Box 26)
  - Paul, Peter (Box 26)
  - PEW Science Program (Box 26)
  - Quantar (Box 26)
  - Radiation Committee (Box 26)
  - Radiation Exposure Limits (Box 26)
  - Radioactive sources (Box 26)
  - Radiation Detection Co. (Box 26)
  - Radiation Committee (Box 27)
  - Ramus Proposal (Box 27)
  - Research in our Dept. (Box 27)
  - Safety (Box 27)
  - Scheurer, J.-N. (Box 27)
  - Schiff lecture (2 folders) (Box 27)
  - Secretarial Personnel (Box 27)
  - Secretary - group (Box 27)
  - Shah (Box 27)
  - Sigmon (Box 27)
  - Sloan Foundation (Box 28)
  - Stoller (Box 28)
  - Superhilac Pac (Box 28)
  - Technicians (Box 28)
  - Voegtle (Box 28)
  - Watson (Box 28)
  - Wells, Don (Box 28)
  - Wells, John (Box 28)
  - Wilkinson, D.H., Dr. (Box 28)
  - Wölfli (Box 28)
  - Xu (Box 28)
  - Zoran (Box 28)
  - Zupančič, Č. (Box 28)
  - Detector Efficiency Curves (Box 28)
  - Stopping (Box 28)
  - Charge Exchange, Yields 6(b) (Box 28)
  - C 12 CPP paper (Box 28)
  - Dr. Meyerhof (Box 28)
  - Faculty Reports (Box 29)
  - Supplementary 9019293 High Energy Atomic Phys. March 1982 (Box 29)
  - Proposals, 1986-87 (4 folders) (Box 29)
  - Final report, 1984-87 (Box 29)
  - Progress reports, 1981-92 (7 folders) (Box 29)
  - Budget continuation request, starting 2-1-90 (Box 29)
  - Progress reports, 1973-75 (Box 30)
  - Progress report, 6/1/76-6/30/77 (Box 30)
  - Progress reports, Nov 1, 1980 - Oct 31, 1981 (Box 30)
  - Progress reports, Dec 15, 1981 - Dec 14, 1982 (Box 30)
  - Progress report, 1986 (Box 30)
  - Check requests & other financial documents, 1983 (Box 30)
  - Progress reports, 1980-82 (Box 31)
  - Petty Cash Records – WEM & other financial documents, 1979-80; n.d. (Box 31)
  - Workshop "Minorities and Women in Physics", 1990 (Box 31)
  - Invited talks (Box 31)
  - Abstracts, 1983-1991 (Box 31)
  - Purchase requisitions and orders, 1985-88 (Box 32)
  - 1988 – Invited Lecture, 20th Int'l Summer School, Nuclear Physics, Poland (Box 32)
  - XIV ICPEAC Conference, Palo Alto, 1985 (Box 32)
  - U.S. – Japan Cooperative Seminar, March 14-18, 1983, etc. (Box 32)
  - Misc. articles by W. Meyerhof (and in a co-authorship), 1969, 1975, 1987, 1993 (4 folders) (Box 32)
  - 4th Int'l Conference on Atomic Physics, July 22-26, 1974, Heidelberg, W. Germany (Box 32)
  - Misc. articles by others, 1987-88; n.d. (5 folders) (Box 32)
  - Misc. articles, abstracts, off prints & related correspondence (by W. Meyerhof and others), 1987-92; n.d. (17 folders) (Box 33)
  - Licenses and Registration State of California (Box 33)
  - Application for CRA approval (Box 33)
  - Radioactive material license material (Box 34)
  - Tandem Radiation Procedures (Box 34)
  - 3 MeV Van de Graaff (Box 34)
  - PH 001-PH 009 (9 folders) (Box 34)
  - Misc. correspondence, PH 010-PH 014 (Box 34)
  - Actual applications, PH 010-PH 014 (Box 34)
  - Actual applications, PH 015-PH 021 (Box 35)
  - Misc. correspondence, PH015-PH022 (Box 35)
  - Misc. financial documents, 1983-91 (Box 35)
  - Correspondence, 1989-91 (Box 35)
  - Documentation 1989-91 (Box 35)
  - Interdept. Requests 1989-91 (Box 36)
  - Stores, 1989-91 (Box 36)
  - Transfer of expense & travel expenses reports, 1989-91 (Box 36)
  - 1985-88 check requests & 1987-88 correspondence (Box 36)
  - 1985-86 correspondence (Box 36)
  - 1985-88 stores requisitions (Box 36)
  - Spooner (Box 36)
  - 1984-88 documentation charges (Box 37)
  - 1985-88 travel expense reports (Box 37)
  - Travel (Box 37)
  - Requisition Orders, Date Chronological, 2 FEV 436 (Box 37)
  - Van de Graaf equipment (Box 38)
  - Draft of the Enclosed H&S Guidelines for Laboratory Space, 1984 (Box 38)
  - Proposal 1990 2 FEV 448 (Box 38)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence 1989-90 (Box 38)
  - References (Box 38)
  - Safety (Box 38)
  - SLAC Expt. (Box 38)
  - Walter Meyerhof (Box 38)
  - 1FEV 404 406 Brazil (Box 38)
  - 1FEV 405 Berlin (Box 38)
  - 2FEV 448 ATO Phys. 1991/92 (Box 38)
  - ISHII (Box 38)
  - Molitoris (Box 38)
  - 1FEV 602 Dean (Box 39)
  - Meyerhof Budget Sheets, 2 FEV 444-94 (Box 39)
  - Meyerhof personal (Box 39)
  - Meetings (Box 39)
  - Morenzoni (Box 39)
  - Montenegro (Box 39)
  - 1FEV 614 (Box 39)
  - Stationery (Box 39)
  - Baxter (Box 39)
  - Belkacem (Box 39)
  - Berkeley (Box 39)
  - Brazil (Box 40)
  - Charlton (Box 40)
  - Chemin (Box 40)
  - Chinese visitors (Box 40)
  - Danzmann (Box 40)
  - Eichler (Box 40)
  - Equipment Loans and Inventory (Box 40)
  - Misc. abstracts, off prints etc. by W. Meyerhof / in a co-authorship, 1972-75 (15 folders) (Box 40)
  - Misc. abstracts, off prints etc. by W. Meyerhof / in a co-authorship, 1976-84; n.d. (25 folders, some are empty) (Box 41)
  - Misc. abstracts, off prints etc. by W. Meyerhof / in a co-authorship, 1984 (cont'd)-86 (5 folders); 1953, 1957 (3 folders) (Box 42)
  - Address cards labeled Meyerhof (Box 42)
  - R. Anholz - Reprints (Box 42)
  - Misc. abstracts, off prints etc. by W. Meyerhof / in a co-authorship, 1958-59, 1962-80, 1982 (21 folders) (Box 43)
  - Misc. abstracts, off prints etc. by W. Meyerhof / in a co-authorship, 1983-89, 1991-96 (12 folders) (Box 44)